Register of the Pavel Mikhaǐlovich Litvinov papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Pavel Mikhaǐlovich Litvinov papers
1933-2011
2016C25
Hoover Institution Archives
6 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box (4.1 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoirs and other writings, notes, printed matter, and photographs relating to political prisoners, civil rights and dissent in the Soviet Union, and to Russian émigré affairs.
Litvinov, Pavel Mikhaĭlovich, 1940-
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2016.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Born in 1940, Pavel Litvinov is a physicist, writer, and Soviet-era dissident. He is the grandson of Maksim (Maxim) Litvinov, the former Russian minister of foreign affairs (1930-1939) and ambassador to the United States (1941-1943).
Litvinov was raised among the Soviet elite, but after Stalin's death in 1953, he became disillusioned with the Soviet system after witnessing the return of family friends from the labor camps. In his twenties, he became acquainted with a group of intellectuals who were following the show-trials of the writers Andrei Siniavskii and Iulii Daniel'. Litvinov was one of eight participants in the 1968 Red Square demonstration against the Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia; the participants raised banners in Czech and Russian supporting Czechoslovak independence. The KGB promptly arrested the protesters and put them on trial two months later. Litvinov was sentenced to five years' exile in Siberia.
In 1974, Litvinov and his family immigrated to the United States, where he taught physics and mathematics at a boarding school in Tarrytown, New York, until his retirement in 2006.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Pavel Litvinov papers include biographical material, correspondence, memoirs and other writings, notes, printed matter, and photographs relating to political prisoners, civil rights and dissent in the Soviet Union, and Russian émigré affairs.
Civil rights--Soviet Union.; Political prisoners--Soviet Union.; Dissenters--Soviet Union.; Russians--United States.
- Biographical File, 1966-2008
  Arrangement Statement
  Arranged chronologically.
  - American passports and other identification documents, 1966-1999 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes Pavel Litvinov's Moscow State University diploma.
  - Records of Pavel Litvinov trial, 1966-1990 (Box-folder 1: 2-5)
    Includes investigative documents, legal complaints, appeals, and other materials relating to Litvinov's trial and exile.
  - Autobiography and curriculum vitae, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Clippings, 1974-2006 (Box-folder 1: 7-10)
    Includes clippings and articles relating to Pavel Litvinov.
  - Certificates of achievement and appreciation, 1981-2008 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    Includes String Quartet no. 3, by Mikko A. Taylor, inscribed and dedicated to P. Litvinov on the occasion of his retirement from teaching.
- Correspondence, 1969-2008
  - General, 1983-2006 (Box-folder 1: 12-13)
    Includes appreciation letters from students and colleagues, short notes, and greeting cards.
  - Asarkan, Aleksandr (Alexander), 1985-2002 (Box-folder 1: 14-15)
  - Birchall, Graeme, 2002 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Buga, Mary Ann, 1990 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Daniel, Aleksandr (Alexander), 1991 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Freed, Florence W., 2007 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Guseinov, Gasan, 1991 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Hamlin, Bryan T., 1991 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Havel, Václav, 1993-2008 (Box-folder 1: 22)
    Includes invitation to the "Festive Gathering on the Occasion of the 40th Anniversary of the 1968 August Events."
  - Kutik, Vitalii Naumovich, 2003 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Lebedev, M., circa 2000 (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Leborg, Carol, 2003 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Litvinov, Mikhail (father), 1995 (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Litvinova, Flora (mother), 1972-1999 (Box-folder 2: 1-2)
  - Litvinova, Nina (sister), 1990-1998 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Litvinov, Pavel M., 1969-1995, undated
    Photocopies of letters from exile and America to his family relating to personal and family matters.
    - Undated (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 2: 5-7)
    - 1970 (Box-folder 2: 8-9)
    - 1971 (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - 1972 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    - 1976 (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - 1980-1985 (Box-folder 2: 13)
    - 1990-1995 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Petrova, Tat'iana Alekseevna, 2004 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Ponomarev, Ivan, circa 2000 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Rerid, Allan, 2004 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Rubin, Inna (Ines), 2000-2001 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Rubina, M., 2002 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Shragin, Boris, 2005 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Svechinskii (Svechinsky), V., circa 2000 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Waite, Jim, 1983 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Weil, Robert, 1997 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Yarim-Agaev, Yuri, 1984 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Zhang, Jizhen, 1990 (Box-folder 3: 10)
- Speeches and Writings, 1968-1999
  - General, 1968-1993 (Box-folder 3: 11-12)
    Includes fragments, drafts, and notes.
  - "Comparing Soviet and American Education,", 1988 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - "Pis'mo iz dal'nego zarubezh'ia,", 1993 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - Interview transcripts, 1993-1999 (Box-folder 3: 15-16)
    Includes interview of Pavel Litvinov and others on human rights; audio transcripts by N. Sorokin.
- International Human Rights Organizations File, 1974-2011
  Arranged alphabetically by name of organization.
  - The Andrei Sakharov Foundation, 2008-2011 (Box-folder 3: 17-18)
    Agenda, speeches, writings, correspondence, and printed matter relating to special meetings and conferences. Includes "Mustafa Dzhemilev and the Struggle for Human Rights," speech by Pavel Litvinov.
  - Committee for the Absorption of Soviet Emigres (CASE), 1974-1992 (Box-folder 3: 19)
    Includes "Certificate of Incorporation" and "Articles of Agreement between CASE and Vladlen Pavlemkov."
  - Freedom of Communications, Inc., 1984-1991 (Box-folder 3: 20-22)
    Includes international funding sources records, correspondence, and annual budget report.
  - Friends of Memorial, Inc., 1997 (Box-folder 3: 23)
    Includes charities registration statement, application for tax-exempt status, and notes.
  - Helsinki Watch Group newsletters, 1979 (Box-folder 3: 24)
  - Hebrew Immigrant Aid Society (HIAS) annual meeting agenda, 1980 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Index on Censorship, 1997 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    Includes correspondence with Pavel Litvinov.
  - "Memorial," international historical and civil rights society, 1974-2003 (Box-folder 4: 3-6)
    Includes program, statements, appeals, correspondence, and printed matter.
  - Moral Re-Armament, Inc. (MRA), 1990-1993 (Box-folder 4: 7-8)
    Includes MRA newsletters, correspondence, and Bryan T. Hamlin's reports about his trips to Moscow.
- Gabriel Superfin File, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  Includes memoranda, correspondence, and other materials related to Gabriel Superfin's career at Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty (RFE/RL).
- Ivy Litvinov File, 1938-1969 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  Includes copies of the Soviet Committee for State Security (KGB) reports on Ivy Litvinov.
- Kontinent, Editorial Board Correspondence, 1981-1985 (Box-folder 4: 11)
- Maksim Maksimovich Litvinov File, 1933-2001 (Box-folder 4: 12-14)
  Clippings and articles relating to Maksim Litvinov. Includes The Elusive Litvinov Memoirs, by Elena Danielson. See also: Box 7.
- Program Corporation of America (PCA), The Lecture Management Company File, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 4: 15-16)
  Includes correspondence and lecturer contracts with Pavel Litvinov.
- Writings by Others, 1973-2007
  Arranged alphabetically by author's name.
  - General, 1993-1999 (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
    Includes articles, interviews, and excerpts regarding human rights violations.
  - Azbel', Mark, Aleksandr and Nina Voronel', "Ierusalimskie razmyshleniia,", 1986 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Glazov, Iurii, "Na chuzhoi storonke, Amerika, 1973-1975,", circa 1980 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Kaplan, Aleksandr E., "Seven in Red Square," coordinator's postings, 1996 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Kim, Iulii, Delo Petra Iakira, 1997 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Kopelev, Lev, "Komu eto nuzhno?," "Pis'mo Solzhenitsynu," Sintaksis, Paris, 1986-2001 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Levin, M. L., "Sorokoud," typescript, 1973 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Losev, Lev, "Zametki pri chtenii Avgusta 1914," broadcast script, Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty (RFE/RL), 1984 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - Maksudov, Sergei, "Ne svoi," typescript, circa 2001 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Roberts, Geoffrey, "Litvinov's Lost Peace, 1941-1946," Journal of Cold War Studies, Vol. 4, No. 2, 2002 (Box-folder 5: 11)
  - Rubin, Ines (Inna), "The Signature Campaign: Excerpts From the Diary of Vitalii A. Rubin," Research Paper No. 60, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, The Soviet and East European Research Centre, Jerusalem, 1985 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Skriakova, E. V., "Razmyshleniia o suti pravozashchitnoi raboty: postanovka problemy," Budushchee Prav Cheloveka v Rossii, Almanac, No. 1, 2007 (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - Yarim-Agaev, Yuri, "Podmena," Neprikosnovennyj zapas: NZ: debaty o politike i kul·ture: zhurnal, 2001 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - Zhebrovska, Anna, "O Pavlike, s kotorym bylo slozhno," typescript, circa 1995 (Box-folder 5: 15)
- Photographs, 1960-2007
  Arranged alphabetically by last name.
  - Fainberg, Viktor, circa 1960 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Ginzburg, Aleksandr and Tat'iana Khodorovich, circa 1970 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - Grigorenko, Petr, circa 1975 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - Iakobson (Yakobson), Anatolii Aleksandrovich, circa 1970 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Kopelev, Lev with family and friends, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - Litvinov, Pavel with family and friends, 1980-2007 (Box-folder 6: 6-10)
  - Sinyavsky, Andrei Donatovich, Maria Vasilievna Rozanova, and Viktor Kalnins, circa 1970 (Box-folder 6: 11)
  - Svetlichnyi, N., 1978 (Box-folder 6: 12)
  - Unidentified, 1970-1990 (Box-folder 6: 13)
- Printed Matter, 1983-2011
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - General, 1993 (Box-folder 5: 16)
    Includes flyers and leaflets.
  - Bardy: ot pervogo litsa, antologiia avtorskoi pesni, by Iurii Vizbor and Iulii Kim, 1993 (Box-folder 5: 17)
  - Ksenofobiia, svoboda sovesti i antiekstremizm v Rossii v 2010 godu, reports, Tsentr "Sova,", 2011 (Box-folder 5: 18)
  - Tribuna, Nos. 1-6, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 5: 19)
    Includes business certificate.
- Clippings, 1973-2011 (Box-folder 6: 14-17)
  Related to the Soviet dissident movement.
- Sound Recording, 1974 July 15 (Box-folder 6: 18)
  One compact sound cassette recording Pavel Litvinov's telephone conversation with Andrei Sakharov.
- Oversize Material, 1933-1990
  Arranged by physical format.
  - Certificate of Honorary Citizenship of the State of Tennessee, 1984 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Honorary Citizenship Award, 1990 (Box-folder 7: 2)
    In recognition of participation in the 1968 Red Square demonstration against the Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia, Prague.
  - Ogonek, 1933 December 5 (Box-folder 7: 3)
    With magazine's cover portrait of the People's Commissar for Foreign Affairs Maksim Maksimovich Litvinov.
  - Photo album, circa 1990 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    Depicts Soviet dissidents with Czech President Václav Havel in recognition of the 1968 Red Square demonstration protesting the Soviet invasion of Czechoslovakia.